Guide to the Lillian Cooper papers CBHM.0023
Center for Brooklyn History
Lillian Cooper papers
circa 1905 - circa 2000
1922-1983
Center for Brooklyn History
Cooper, Lillian, 1905-1995
Cooper-Novack, Gemma
Kobbe, Herman, 1884-1966
Agris, Minerva
Borden, Helen
Bush, Rose
Clayton, Kit (Kathleen)
Cooper, Belle
Cooper, Ben
Cooper, Celia
Pazeian, Gertrude Cooper
Ehrlich, Lillian
Ehrlich, Pessie
Cooper, George
Feldman, Ruth Elaine
Ferholt, Ruth
Ferholt, Edward
Fish, Gladys
Fosseur, Margot (Marguerite)
Freedman-Beuner, Sara
Fried, Bernard J.
Fried, Cele
Friedler, Frans W.
Goodridge, Helen
Hanson, Alice
Hendricks, Sarah
Hohl, Louise
Holtzman, Filia Ravitz
Horton, Jacob
Kimels, Sophie
Hunt, Emily Kinne
Ingerman, Eugenia
Kauffman, Frank T.
Kazaras, Frieda Scher
Kellogg, Gladys
Klein, Gertrude W., 1893-1986
Brown, Alfred A.
Laffer, Sonya
MacGregor, Martha
MacQueen, Ena
Marcellus, Muriel
Marcellus, Jane
Martin, Mary E.
Mehl, Mildred
Moseley, Mary Inez
Muller, Florence
Newman, Edward S.
Nissen, Dorothy
Norton, Lillian
O'Brien, Molly
Ogden, Josephine
Rojas, Bonifacio
Ruskin, Gertrude M.
Stern, Jerry
Stern, Nettie Petersilie
Schneiderman, Ann
Schwartz, Martha C.
Shapiro, Anna Stern
Shumway, Naomi
Siegal, Max
Silver, Belle
Skillman, Maude
Solveson, Gladys V.
Spero, Anne
Stanton, Dorothy
Stephens, Annette
Stephens, Lou
Stephens, Laney
Stickney, Pauline
Gruher, Hanford
Gruher, Halie
Gruher, Dawn Stuart
Tatum, Alice
Weintraub, Sylvia Steckler
Willis, Jessie Lee
Wilson, Mary
Wilson, Dorothy
Wilson, Floyd
Wilson, Ruth
CBHM.0023
11.63 Linear Feet in 23 manuscript boxes and one oversize box.
The Lillian Cooper papers consist of correspondence, journals, writings, licenses and certificates, and photographs of Lillian Cooper, a socialist writer and teacher from Brooklyn.
Scope and Contents
The Lillian Cooper papers consist of correspondence, journals, photographs, certificates and diplomas, and ephemera relating to the life of writer and teacher Lillian Cooper. The bulk of the collection is made up of correspondence between Cooper and her family, friends, and colleagues. The rest of the collection is published and unpublished writings in journals and notebooks, and files related to her relationship with Herman Kobbé and their Holly Point Project. Her papers include photographs of her immediate and extended family.
Related Materials
Center for Brooklyn History hold the following related poets' collections:
- Marie Trommer collection, 1906-1959 (ARC.101)
- Bob Heman collection, 1968-1996 (CBHM.0026)
- Maude White and Charles H. Hardie papers, 1881-1947 (ARC.298)
Related materials at other institutions include:
- Pennsylvania State Archives, McCalmont Family papers, 1925-1947 (MG-371)
- New York University, Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, Gertrude W. Klein papers, circa 1910-1989 (TAM.368)
- Duke University Libraries, Hope Stoddard papers in the John Hall Wheelock collection, 1935-1979 (RL.01372)
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1922-1977
Series 2: Writings, 1933-1983
Series 3: Administrative files, 1935-circa 1980
Series 4: Herman Kobbé papers, 1935-1947
Series 5: Photographs, circa 1905-circa 2000
Biographical Note
Lillian Cooper was born on December 11, 1907 at the Jewish Hospital on Classon and St. Marks Avenues in Brooklyn, New York. Her parents, Ben Cooper and Celia Cooper (née Belzman), had recently immigrated from the Pale of Settlement (listed as Russia in censuses) and Lillian was their first child. Ben Cooper's occupation listed on Lillian's birth certificate was bookbinder.
The family moved several times in Brooklyn. At the time of Lillian's birth, the Coopers were living at 17 Barrett Street in Brownsville. Then they moved to an address on Lorimer Street. Ben and Celia Cooper had two more children: Gertrude (1910-1972) and George (1912-1963). In 1918, they were living at 609 Gates Avenue. In 1930, Lillian Cooper was still living with her parents at 570 Gates Avenue in Bedford-Stuyvesant. The Coopers finally settled in Brighton Beach at 3130 Brighton 6th Street.
Cooper graduated from Eastern District High School in 1925. She received a New York State scholarship to complete her BA degree at Hunter College, graduating in 1930. She also completed some graduate coursework at Columbia University in the late 1930s/early 1940s. Cooper was certified as an elementary school teacher. She got a job at Greenup High School in Greenup, Kentucky where she lived and worked until 1933 when she then moved to work temporary jobs in Philadelphia and Arkansas.
In the mid-1930s, Cooper met Herman Kobbé, an architect and candidate for New York Lieutenant Governor on the 1934 Socialist Party ticket. Cooper worked as a social investigator in the Department of Welfare for the City of New York from 1935 to 1942.
Kobbé and Cooper lived together in an apartment at 209 Washington Park in Brooklyn. Lillian Cooper and Herman Kobbé traveled to Mexico together and lived there for a time. In 1943, they bought a farm, nicknamed Chinaberry House, in Leesville, South Carolina.
In the late 1940s, Cooper and Kobbé worked together on the Holly Point Project, a plan for a children's development center on their land around Lake Murray, South Carolina. The plan included a boarding school, programs for parents, and vacation opportunities for city children. Kobbé was the director and Cooper worked as research assistant. Cooper and Kobbé's relationship ended around 1948.
In the mid-1950s, Cooper worked in the College of Engineering at the University of Florida, Gainesville. When she moved back to New York, Cooper continued teaching in New York City public schools and took courses in writing at New York University and the Herzl Institute. She submitted fiction pieces and poems to publications, often using the pen name Joan Kinner. She also took on freelance, research, editing, and writing projects.
Lillian Cooper died on September 19, 1995 in New Jersey.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gemma Cooper-Novack, 2023.
Authors, American; Labor unions--Organizing; Teachers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Correspondence; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Photographs; Writings (document genre); Notebooks; American poetry -- Women authors; Poetry; Licenses; Certificates; Jewish women; Socialism and education; Women socialists; Cooper-Novack, Gemma; Kobbe, Herman, 1884-1966; Cooper, Lillian, 1905-1995
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1922-1977
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in two ways. The first folders of correspondence are arranged alphabetically. For correspondents that are well represented in the collection, their correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent and chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Correspondence, 1922-1977, is made up of correspondence between Lillian Cooper, her family, friends, and professional contacts. The bulk of the correspondence is from the 1930s through the 1940s. Topics in the correspondence include labor organizing, socialism, writing, and the experience of being Jewish in the United States. Prominent correspondents include dancer Maudelle Bass Weston, Gertrude W. Klein, one of the first women elected to the City Council of New York, Gertrude M. Ruskin, Comptroller of the United Service for New Americans and Analyst for the Displaced Persons Commission, author Sylvia Chatfield Bates, artist Michael Baxte, German philosopher Beate Berwin, and German writer Gustav Regler.
  Correspondence is also present in the Administrative Files and Herman Kobbé papers, especially between Cooper, Kobbé and Laney Stephens.
  - [Correspondence], 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - [Correspondence], circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Correspondence], 1933-1938 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
  - [Correspondence], circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Correspondence], 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 12-23)
  - [Correspondence], circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Correspondence], 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 25-27)
  - [Correspondence], 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
  - [Correspondence], 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - [Christmas cards], circa 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - [Hanukkah cards], circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Kentucky A - G, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - [Minerva Agris], 1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - [Maudelle Bass], 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - [Sylvia Bates], 1942 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - [Michael Baxte], 1945 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - [Beate C. Berwin], 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - [Helen Borden], 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - [Rose Bush], 1934 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - [Winifred Chappell], 1941 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - [Kathleen (Kit) Clayton], 1933-1948 (Box 1, Folder 43, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - [Belle Cooper], 1936-1941 (Box 2, Folder 4-8)
  - [Belle Cooper], 1945-1948 (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
  - [Belle Cooper], 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - [Gertrude and Belle Cooper], 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - [Ben and Celia Cooper], 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - [Ben and Celia Cooper], 1930-1938 (Box 2, Folder 17-27)
  - [Ben and Celia Cooper], 1945-1954 (Box 2, Folder 28-31, Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - [Ben, Celia, Gertrude Cooper], 1925-1933 (Box 3, Folder 10-15)
  - [Cooper Family], 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
  - [Lillian Cooper to Cooper Family], 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
  - [Ben, Celia, George Cooper], 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - [George Cooper], 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - [George Cooper], 1930 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - [George Cooper], 1932-1940 (Box 3, Folder 25, Box 24, Folder 6)
  - [George Cooper], 1945-1947 (Box 23, Folder 8-9, Box 3, Folder 26)
  - [George and Gertrude Cooper], 1929-1946 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
  - [George and Belle Cooper], 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - [The Ehrlich Family], 1931 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - [Lillian Ehrlich], 1925-1930 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - [Pessie Ehrlich], 1933 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - [Ruth Feldman], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [Ruth (Ruthie) Brodsky Feferholz Ferholt], 1934-1941 (Box 4, Folder 2-8)
  - [Ruth (Ruthie) Brodsky Feferholz Ferholt], 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 9-15)
  - [Ruth and Edward Feferholz Ferholt], 1940-1942 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - [Gladys Fish], 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - [Marguerite (Margot) Fosseur], 1925-1934 (Box 4, Folder 18-20)
  - [Sara Freedman-Beuner], 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - [Bernard J. Fried], 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - [Bernard J. Fried], 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 23-28)
  - [Bernard J. Fried], 1952 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - [Bernard and Cele Fried], 1947 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - [Frans W. Friedler], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - [Helen Goodridge], 1945 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - [Alice Hanson], 1935 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - [Sarah Hendricks], 1933 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - [Louise Hohl], 1934 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - [Filia Ravitz Holtzman], 1926-1947 (Box 4, Folder 36-39, Box 5, Folder 1-7)
  - [Filia Ravitz Holtzman], circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - [Filia Ravitz Holtzman], 1952 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - [Jacob and Mrs. Horton], 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - [Sophie Kimels], 1922 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - [Sophie Kimels], 1926-1928 (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - [Emily Kinne Hunt], 1940-1942 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - [Emily Kinne Hunt], 1946 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - [Emily Kinne Hunt], circa 1949 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - [Eugenia Ingerman], circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - [Frank T. Kauffman], 1947 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - [Frieda Scher Kazaras], 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 23-25)
  - [Frieda Scher Kazaras], 1945 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - [Gladys Kellogg], 1946 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - [Gertrude W. Klein], 1923-1940 (Box 5, Folder 28-40, Box 6, Folder 1-3, 11, Box 23, Folder 7)
  - [Gertrude W. Klein], circa 1940 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - [Gertrude W. Klein], 1941-1948 (Box 6, Folder 5-10)
  - [Lillian Cooper to Gertrude W. Klein], 1929-1936 (Box 6, Folder 12-18)
  - [Alfred A. Brown to Gertrude W. Klein], 1926 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - [Sonya Laffer], 1926-1932 (Box 6, Folder 20-23)
  - [Martha MacGregor], 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - [Ena MacQueen], 1940-1942 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - [Ena MacQueen], 1945 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - [Muriel Marcellus], 1930-1933 (Box 6, Folder 27-29)
  - [Muriel Marcellus and Jane Marcellus], 1931-1934 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - [Mary E. Martin], 1931-1934 (Box 6, Folder 31-32)
  - [David McCalmont, Jr.], 1946 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - [Mildred Mehl], 1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - [Mary Inez Moseley], 1932-1936 (Box 7, Folder 3-7)
  - [Florence Muller], 1925-1932 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - [Cecyle Feldman Neidle], 1940-1941 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - [Cecyle Feldman Neidle], 1945-1946 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - [Neo-Seminar], circa 1940 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - [Edward S. Newman], 1939-1942 (Box 7, Folder 12-13, Box 24, Folder 1)
  - [Edward S. Newman], 1945-1947 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - [Dorothy Nissen], 1930-1933 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - [Dorothy Nissen], 1940-1942 (Box 7, Folder 16-18)
  - [Lillian Norton], 1932-1947 (Box 7, Folder 19-22)
  - [Molly O'Brien], 1926-1934 (Box 7, Folder 23-25)
  - [Josephine Ogden], 1932-1933 (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
  - [Josephine Ogden], circa 1935 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - [Josephine Ogden], 1935 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - [Josephine Ogden], 1937 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - [Gertrude Cooper Pazeian], 1926-1945 (Box 7, Folder 31-36, Box 8, Folder 1-22)
  - [Gertrude Cooper Pazeian], circa 1945 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - [Gertrude Cooper Pazeian], 1946-1950 (Box 8, Folder 24-29)
  - [Katharine Pease], 1948 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - [Gustav Regler], 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - [Bonifacio Rojas], 1946-1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - [Gertrude M. Ruskin], 1924-1939 (Box 9, Folder 2-35)
  - [Gertrude M. Ruskin], circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - [Gertrude M. Ruskin], 1940-1951 (Box 10, Folder 2-8)
  - [Jerry Stern], 1931 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1925-1926 (Box 10, Folder 10-11)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1929-1934 (Box 10, Folder 12-17, Box 23, Folder 6)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1938-1940 (Box 10, Folder 18-19)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], circa 1940 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1940-1942 (Box 10, Folder 21-22)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1945-1946 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - [Nettie Petersilie Stern], 1952 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - [Ann Schneiderman], 1945-1947 (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - [Martha C. Schwartz], 1940 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1927 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1929 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], circa 1930 (Box 10, Folder 29-32)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1930-1936 (Box 10, Folder 33-38, Box 11, Folder 1)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1939-1941 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - [Anna Stern Shapiro], 1950 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - [Naomi Shumway], 1939-1942 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - [Max Siegal], 1947 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - [Belle Silver], 1923-1927 (Box 11, Folder 9-22)
  - [Belle Silver], 1936 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - [Maude Skillman], 1945-1946 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - [Gladys V. Solveson], 1933-1934 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - [Ruth Sonneborn], 1941 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - [Anne Spero], 1926 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - [Anne Spero], 1929-1933 (Box 11, Folder 28-31)
  - [Anne Spero], 1935-1940 (Box 11, Folder 32-33)
  - [Anne Spero], circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - [Anne Spero], 1941-1942 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - [Anne Spero], 1945-1946 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - [Anne Spero], 1948 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - [Dorothy Stanton], 1945-1946 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - [Annette Stephens], 1944-1946 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - [Annette and Lou Stephens], 1938-1948 (Box 12, Folder 6-9)
  - [Laney Stephens], 1950 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - [Pauline Stickney], 1934 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - [Pauline Stickney], 1937-1938 (Box 12, Folder 12-14)
  - [Pauline Stickney], 1942 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - [Pauline Stickney], 1948 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - [Hope Stoddard], 1933-1934 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - [Hanford and Halie Gruher, Dawn Stuart], 1945-1947 (Box 12, Folder 18-19)
  - [Alice Carr Baker Tatum], 1931-1942 (Box 12, Folder 20-27)
  - [Alice Carr Baker Tatum], 1947-1951 (Box 12, Folder 28)
  - [Sylvia Steckler Weintraub], 1926-1929 (Box 12, Folder 29-32)
  - [Sylvia Steckler Weintraub], circa 1930 (Box 12, Folder 33)
  - [Sylvia Steckler Weintraub], 1931-1934 (Box 12, Folder 34-39)
  - [Sylvia Steckler Weintraub], 1947-1948 (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - [Jessie Lee Willis], 1935 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - [Mary Wilson], circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - [Mary Wilson], 1942 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - [Dorothy, Mary, and Floyd Wilson], 1933 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - [Dorothy and Mary Wilson], 1936-1941 (Box 13, Folder 7-11)
  - [Floyd and Dorothy Wilson], 1939-1941 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - [Ruth Wilson], circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 13)
- Series 2: Writings, 1933-1983
  This series is organized chronologically.
  Series 2: Writings, 1933-1983, contains published and unpublished works, mostly short fiction pieces and poetry, by Lillian Cooper. Cooper also published and submitted pieces under the pen name Joan Kinner. The works are typewritten and handwritten in notebooks and calendar books. Pieces submitted to specific journals or conferences, or for writing courses are in folders titled with that journal, conference, or course.
  - [Notebook], 1933-1934 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - S. C. Bates [Sylvia Chatfield Bates], 1939-1941 (Box 13, Folder 15-16)
  - [Notebook], circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - ["Once upon a time in the Island of Milos…"], circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - ["Turkey for Star" play], circa 1940 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - New York University, Department of Journalism, Short Story Manuscripts, 1941 (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - Decade of Short Stories, 1944-1945 (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - [Poem], 1945 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - [Journal entries], 1945 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "The Trailing Infantile", circa 1945 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - "Undercat Underpigeon", circa 1945 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Wolf are you Ready?", cira 1945 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - [Writings], 1948-1949 (Box 14, Folder 6-7)
  - [Calendar], 1949-1950 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - "You Think Too Much", 1950 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - [Drawings], circa 1950 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - [Notebook], 1950-1951 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - [Notebook], 1953-1956 (Box 14, Folder 12-14, Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Sociology and Social Research, Volume 42, Number 1, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - [Calendar], 1958-1959 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - [Notebook], 1959 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - [Journal entries], 1961-1962 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Bread Loaf [Writers' Conference], 1964 (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
  - [Writings], 1965 (Box 14, Folder 21, Box 15, Folder 1)
  - [Notebook], 1966 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - [Notes], 1967 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - [Writings], 1967 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - [Notebook], 1966-1968 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - [Writings], 1963-1972 (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
  - [Notebook], 1971 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - [Journal entries], 1971 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - [Writings], 1971 (Box 15, Folder 11-12)
  - Age [Poetry], 1972-1977 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - [Writings], 1972-1982 (Box 15, Folder 14-15)
  - Human Species [Poetry], 1973-1975 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - City [Poetry], 1973-1976 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - California [Poetry], 1973-1975 (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - [Writings], 1973-1982 (Box 15, Folder 19-21)
  - [Wormwood Review, Issue 56], 1974 (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - [Poetry], 1974 (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - [Writings], 1974 (Box 15, Folder 24-26)
  - Sickness? [Poetry], 1974-1976 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Britain [Poetry], 1974-1977 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - [Notebook], 1975 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - [Writings], 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 3-4)
  - [Notebook], 1976-1978 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
  - [Writings], 1976-1979 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Children's Games [Poetry], 1976-1981 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - [Writings], 1977 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Articles, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - [Calendar], 1977-1978 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - [Notebook], 1978 (Box 16, Folder 12-13)
  - "The Poets of Herzl Institute", 1978 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - [Writings], 1978 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Shakespeare Survey [class notebook], 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - [Writings], 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - [Hunter College, Poetry Writing Workshop notebook], 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - [Writings], 1978-1979 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - NYQ (N.P.) [The New York Quarterly (Not Published)], 1979 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Herzl [Notebook], 1979 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - [Notebook], 1979-1980 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - [Writings], 1979-1982 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - [Journal entries], 1982 (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Herzl notes, 1979-1983 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - [The World Guild Magazine, Volume 5, Number 3], 1980 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - [Notebook], 1980 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - [Writings], 1980 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Herzl notes, 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - [Notebook], 1980-1983 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - [Journal entries], 1981-1982 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - [Notebook], 1981-1982 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - [Poetry], 1981-1982 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - [Writings], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - [Notebook], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
  - [Writings], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Herzl Institute, Nancee Haft's workshop, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - [Writings], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Typed lines (for revision?), 1982 (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - [Poetry], 1982 (Box 18, Folder 14-15)
  - [Notebook], 1982-1983 (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - [Writings], 1982-1983 (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - [Notes], 1983 (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - [Writings], 1983 (Box 18, Folder 19-20)
- Series 3: Administrative Files, 1935 - circa 1980
  Series 3: Administrative Files, 1935 - circa 1980, includes licenses, teaching certificates, and other paperwork regarding Lillian Cooper's teaching career, courses she took, and conferences she attended; resumes; a handwritten will from 1969; and immigration documents related to William Hirschel Eichhorn whose relationship to Lillian Cooper is unknown. The bulk of this series consists of correspondence and paperwork related to the Holly Point Project, a collaboration between Lillian Cooper and Herman Kobbé to build a children's development center on their land around Lake Murray, South Carolina including a boarding school, programs for parents, and a camp for city children. Related to these files are files regarding Cooper and Kobbé's break-up around 1948.
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  - [Board of Education of the City of New York elementary school diploma], 1921 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - [Eastern District High School and University of the State of New York diplomas], 1925 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - [Hunter College diploma], 1930 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - 209 [Washington Park] studio, circa 1936 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - [Civil Service Commission service rating], 1939-1940 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - [Letter to Herman Kobbé], 1940 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Drawings, circa 1940 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - [William Hirschel Eichhorn citizenship documents], 1946-1957 (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - HK + HPP [Herman Kobbé and Holly Point Project], 1935-1950 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - [Holly Point Project summary], 1947 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé] farm business, 1943-1944 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - The Farm, 1944-1945 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé] farm business, 1944-1951 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Camp [Holly Point Project], 1947 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé] Legal, 1948 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Applications for writing fellowship, 1948-1949 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - HK and HPP [Herman Kobbé and Holly Point Project], 1945-1952 (Box 19, Folder 13-19)
  - [Holly Point Project planning documents], 1947-1948 (Box 19, Folder 20-25, Box 20, Folder 1)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé] Project, 1948 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Laney - Project [Laney Stephens, Holly Point Project], 1948 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Stephens [Laney Stephens, Holly Point Project], 1926-1948 (Box 20, Folder 4-6)
  - HK [Herman Kobbé] Project, 1947-1948 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - Staff, 1948 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Board, 1948 (Box 20, Folder 9)